太阳
The sun
施予光线和生命
giver of light and the life
赤道的太阳最猛烈
shines most powerfully at the Equator.
太阳在这里驱动生物丰富的区域
Here, it powers an
extraordinarily rich zone of life.
三大洲三大洋的瞩目奇异的动物
Brilliant and bizarre species from
three continents... three oceans.
赤道不只是地图上的一条线
而是自然的强大力量
More than a line on a map...
Equator is a powerful force of nature.
赤道
太平洋
海洋的力量
加拉帕哥斯群岛位于赤道
The Galapagos Islands lie on the Equator
却不是热带天堂
but they're no tropical paradise.
太平洋为这些沙漠岛
带来富庶和饥荒
The Pacific Ocean brings both fortune
and famine to this desert islands.
海洋在加拉帕哥斯群岛
营造了奇怪和似非而是的国度
At the Palapagos islands the ocean has
created a strange improbable realm.
这是龙的栖身之所
This is a place for dragons.
海生鬣蜥栖息于此
因为它们能够驾驭海洋的力量
Marine iguanas livs here because they
can harness the power of the ocean.
海洋的力量来自赤道太阳
The ocean's power comes from the Equatorial sun.
让带来食物和矿物的水流翻腾
it sets in motion great currents
that bring food and minerals here
这些是喂饱很多动物的宝物
riches to feed many.
但海流不止食物丰富，而且寒冷
But they're not just rich
the ocean currents are cold
企鹅正适合这种寒冷
cold enough for penguins.
企鹅在赤道除了在
加拉帕哥斯群岛还能在哪里游泳
Where else but at the Galapagos Islands
could a penguin swim at the Equitor?
蜥蜴只有在这里才能在水下草地
像羊一样吃草
And only here can a lizard graze
like an underwater meadow.
但有时海洋收回水流和宝物
But sometimes the ocean withdraws
the currents and their riches
动物在这些岛屿上就会朝不保夕
then there's hardship on
these islands of uncertainty.
即使饥荒出现也有希望
Even in the face of famine, there's hope
但繁殖无异于冒险
but breeding is a gamble
冒险总是没有好结果
and gamblers often lose.
海洋带给加拉帕哥斯群岛
的宝物和荒芜来自太阳
The riches and desolation that the ocean brings
to the Galapagos Islands are driven by the the sun.
在赤道太平洋，
Out across the Equatorial Pacific,
威力无穷的太阳
将水面温度提升至近摄氏30度
the immensely sun heats surface
water to nearly 30 degrees Celsius.
温暖潮湿空气大量上升
warm moist air rises in such
huge amounts,
从太空往下看
赤道是一条沸腾云层的线
that from space
the Equator is visible as a line of boiling cloud.
下面吸进来的凉气因地球转动
流到西面
Cool air drawn in from below is
swept west by the spin of the earth.
这些是贸易风
These are the trade winds
贸易风在赤道相撞
and they collide at the Equator,
产生雷雨和暴雨
creating thunderstorms and heavy rain.
帕米拉环礁是辽阔太平洋中部
少数遭受洪水侵扰的地方
Palmyra Atoll is one of the few specks of land in
the vast central Pacific to receive this deluge.
这些小岛也位于赤道
These small islands also lie on the equator.
和加拉帕哥斯群岛完全不同
They are completely different
from the Galapagos Islands
但两种岛屿的动物都由海流塑造
yet life on both is shaped by the power of ocean currents.
尽管这繁茂的热带天堂
几乎每天下雨
Although it rains nearly every day
in this lush tropical paradise,
却总是炎热，总是夏季
it's always hot always summer.
在水量充足的温暖下
皮孙木长至30米高
In the well-watered warmth,
Pisonia trees tower to thirty metres
很少热带环礁有长着巨树的雨林
there are very few tropical atolls
with a rainforest of giant trees.
在下面的潮湿阴影里
是巨型椰子蟹
and in the damp shade below,
giant coconut crabs.
一只雄性大椰子蟹可重13公斤
A big male can weigh 13 kilogram,
脚可长逾半米
with legs that span more than half a metre.
椰子蟹的主食是新鲜椰子
全年都能吃到
The crabs' main food is fresh coconuts,
that are available all year round.
椰子蟹是全球最大的陆地
无脊椎动物
Coconut crabs are the largest
terrestrial invertebrates in the world.
它们有巨型前螯，
可将骨肉剪碎
They have massive front claws,
strong enough to strip flesh from bone
即使如此，几只蟹要几天才能
剥开这椰子
even so, it'll take a team of
crabs days to husk this coconut.
除了椰子，
Apart from coconut,
这里食物不多
there's often not much to eat here
但椰子蟹几乎什么都吃
but the crabs eat practically anything.
它们在这些无人岛屿上繁衍
没有天敌
They thrive on these uninhabited
islands and have no predators.
它们唯一的威胁来自其他椰子蟹
their only threats come from each other.
椰子蟹是林地霸王
Coconut crabs are the undisputed
rulers of the forest floor
但天空和树顶属于海鸟
but the skies and tree tops
belong to the seabirds.
近30种鸟类来这里筑巢
Nearly thirty species come here to nest.
帕米拉环礁是赤道太平洋
海鸟饲养幼儿少数的岛屿之一
Palmyra Atoll is one of only a few islands in the
equatorial Pacific where seabirds can raise their young.
一只红脚鲣鸟幼鸟在树的高处
嗷嗷待哺
High in a tree,
a red-footed booby chick waits to be fed.
鲣鸟依靠高树筑巢
The boobies depend on the tall trees for nesting
但树也依靠这些红脚夺目的鸟
but the trees also depend on these
birds with spectacular red feet.
一只红脚鲣鸟为饥饿的幼鸟觅食
To find food for its hungry chick,
大部份时间都在海上寻找飞鱼
a red-footed booby spends most of its time
far out at sea, searching for flying fish
这是困难漫长的工作
it's a long difficult job
温暖海洋就像毫无生命的沙漠
the warm ocean is like a lifeless desert.
每天成年红脚鲣鸟将太平洋
微量食物带回岛上
Each day, the adults bring the Pacific's
meagre offerings back to the island.
食物仅够一对红脚鲣鸟
喂养一只幼鸟
There's only ever enough food for a pair
of red-footed boobies to raise one chick.
如果幼鸟死亡
if a chick dies,
父母要等到下一年才会交配
its parents won't breed again
until next year.
椰子蟹什么都吃
Coconut crabs eat anything
包括死幼鸟
including dead chicks.
但这些馋嘴鬼不是鲣鸟留下的
东西唯一受惠者
But these eager undertakers aren't the only ones
that benefit from what theboobies' leave behind.
鲣鸟送给森林一份珍贵礼物
The boobies give a precious gift to the forest
它们的排泄物是皮孙木需要的
丰富鸟粪肥料
Their waste is a rich guano fertiliser
that Pisonia trees depend on.
森林需要海鸟
The forest needs the seabirds
还有每年落在帕米拉环礁的
近4.5米雨水
and also the nearly four and a half metres of
rain that falls on Palmyra Atoll each year.
尽管动物几乎每天都要忍受暴雨
Though its animals must endure
a rainstorm nearly every day,
这岛屿是渗水珊瑚沙形成的
the island is made of porous coral sand
雨水很快流走
rainwater quickly drains away,
椰子蟹要喝水的话
就要收集身上滴下的水
To get a drink, a crab collects
water dripping off its own body
用一根平时用来清理鳃的细腿
using a tiny leg that it normally
uses to clean its gills.
海鸟在风暴大作时也继续寻找
飞鱼喂饱幼鸟
Even during a storm, seabirds continue their
endless search for flying fish to feed their chicks.
雨和海鸟粪制造的远不止满布
椰子蟹和皮孙木的丰沃森林花园
Rain and seabird guano have created much more than this
lush forest garden of coconut crabs and Pisonia trees.
暴雨溶解了叶子上的干海鸟粪
Heavy rain dissolves dried guano off leaves
冲进渗水珊瑚沙
and washes it down through
the porous coral sand.
这液体现在是独特花园的肥料
This liquid is now fertilizer
for a very different garden.
地上的营养丰富了帕米拉的环礁
nutrients from the land enrich
Palmyra's fringing reef.
没有海鸟粪，这些水域会和
周边海洋一样荒芜
Without seabird guano,these waters would
be as barren as the surrounding ocean
但一群刺尾鱼吃着营养
丰富的藻类
but a school of convict
surgeonfish graze rich algae,
在上面得到养份
fertilised from above.
珊瑚礁看来像是大花园
The coral reef looks like a vast garden,
却是几百万个小动物组成的
but it' one made up of millions of tiny animals.
每个珊瑚都是水螅虫群落
Each coral is a colony of polyps,
全都会过滤流经海流的食物
all filtering food from the passing current.
但珊瑚水螅虫成功的真正秘密
But the real secret to a coral polups' success
是藏在组织之内的微型花园
are the minute gardens,
buried inside, buried in the tissue.
几百万个微型共生藻 为自己
Millions of zooxanthellae, microscopic
algae, make food for themselves
和寄生珊瑚制造食物
以光合作用
and their host coral,
by photosynthesis
利用赤道太阳的力量
by harnessing the power of the equatorial sun.
这植物、动物和太阳间
难以置信的关系
This incredible relationship,
betwen plants and animals and sun,
建立了巨型珊瑚堡垒
has built a great coral fortress.
珊瑚快速成礁
Yet as fast as the corals build the reef,
有些栖息者却要捣毁珊瑚礁
some inhabitants break it down.
一只隆头鹦哥咬破珊瑚硬骨架找
里面的水螅虫
A bumphead parrotfish chews the coral's
hard skeleton to get at the polyps inside.
但它既破坏又建设
But it's as much a builder as destroyer.
它排泄出来的珊瑚是沙
It excretes the coral as sand
沙可以堆成岛屿和沙滩
sand that helps buid the
island and its beaches.
帕米拉的珊瑚礁栖息着几百种鱼
Palmyra's reef is home to
hundreds of fish species.
18种蝴蝶鱼栖身于此
Eighteen species of
butterfly fish live here,
有些只吃珊瑚水螅虫
some so specialised they eat
nothing but coral polyps.
它们的嘴巴像钳子
进食时准确而小心
With mouths shaped like forceps,
they're precise and careful eaters.
清洁隆头鱼靠其他鱼维生
A cleaner wrasse makes its living off other fish
清除寄生虫是不俗的生意
parasite removal is a thriving business.
在赤道太阳每天照射12小时
At the Equator, the sun shines
for twelve hours every day
但12小时黑暗里生命没有停止
but life doesn't stop during
the twelve hours of darkness.
鲣鸟仍在海洋上觅食
boobies still feed out in the open ocean.
但礁上已经面目全非
But on the reef, much changes.
隆头鹦哥身上的颜色
晚上变成黄褐色
A bumphead parrotfish is dressed
in drab night colours,
睡觉的时候隐藏自己
to hide as it sleeps.
一群浮游生物浮上海面觅食
Swarms of zooplankton rise
to the surface to feed
它们被鬼魅般的动物吃掉
and are fed upon by ghosty figures.
魟的双翼长近三米
Manta rays with wings spanning
nearly three metres swoop and dance
每晚在这里吸食宝贵食物
as they suck up the riches
available here every night.
珊瑚在荒芜的赤道太平洋中心
制造了丰饶绿洲
The corals have created a rich oasis in
the middle of the barren Equatorial Pacific.
但这么多种鱼和珊瑚怎么会在
贫乏海洋中间的小环礁共存？
But how did so many different fish and corals come to populate
this tiny, islated atoll in the middle of an empty ocean?
太阳和地球转动形成强烈贸易风
The sun and spin of the earth
create trade winds so powerful
贸易风吹动两大团水
向西太平洋移动
they move two great masses of water
towards the western Pacific.
结果是海面上升，然后向下流动
The result is a raisd sea level,
which then flows back downhill,
沿赤道东流
eastward along the Equator,
形成宽几百公里的逆流
as a counter-current, a few
hundred kilometres wide.
帕米拉环礁就在它的途中
Palmyra Atoll lies directly in its path.
逆流将很多鱼卵和珊瑚幼虫
The counter cuttent brings eggs
and larvae of many fish and corals
由亚洲边缘的珊瑚礁
from reefs on the edge of Asia
这一群年轻海洋生物
让帕米拉环礁
this bounty of young marine life makes Palmyra Atoll
比在海流以外的夏威夷等
岛群要丰饶得多
much richer than island groups such as Hawaii,
that lie outside the current's fiow.
很多帕米拉生物在
流经海流诞下后代
In their turn, many Palmyra species launch
their offspring into the passing current.
在一月最高潮时交配的刺尾鱼
排出大量精子和卵子
On the highest tide of the month mating
surgeonfish release clouds of sperm and eggs.
很多受精卵被外流潮水
冲离珊瑚礁
Many fertilized eggs are swept away
from the reef on the outgoing tide,
在流动缓慢的逆流里向东
踏上未知旅程
to face an uncertain journey east,
in the slow-moving counter current.
卵子几天内就会孵成幼体
Within days the eggs hatch into larvae.
几星期后变成小鱼
After a few weeks they develop into tiny fish.
孵化后两个月内随波逐流的小鱼
需要停留在珊瑚礁上
Within two months of hatching the hopeful
travellers need to settle on a reef.
但最接近陆地的是
加拉帕哥斯群岛
But the nearest land is
the Galapagos Islands,
要向东前进五个月
five months travel to the east.
它们的水流太慢了
Their current is too slow
即使猎兽不吃它们
even if predators don't get them,
小鱼也会时日无多
the young fish will run out of time.
在逆流底下
Far below the counter current,
较快的克伦威尔海流
也沿赤道东流
the faster Cromwell Current
is also flowing east along the Equator.
它带着最远来自南极的深海海水
It carries deep ocean water
from as far away as Antarctica.
它终于浮到水面
It finally rises to the surface
在加拉帕哥斯群岛西面
up the flanks of the western Galapagos Islands
水域非常寒冷，却意味生机勃勃
its waters are very cold,
却意味生机勃勃
yet they hold the promise of life.
水流含有大量溶解矿物
The current is rich in dissolved minerals
这些营养遇上赤道太阳
就会产生奇迹
and when these nutrients meet the
equatorial sun, a miracle occurs.
矿物喂饱了微型植物
例如矽藻
The minerals feed microscopic plants,
such as diatoms
它们在阳光照射的水面繁殖
and in the sunlit surface
waters they reproduce,
再次分开
生命迅速繁衍
dividing again and again,
in an explosion of life.
这些繁殖迅速的浮游生物将
海洋变成黑压压一片
These dense plankton blooms turn
the sea into a murky soup that
能喂养很多动物
feeds many species,
包括一种不平凡的猎兽
including an unusual predator -
不能飞行的巨型鸬鹚
the giant, flightless cormorant.
这小鸬鹚群是繁忙之地
This small cormorant colony is a busy place
有些要喂养大幼鸟
Some pairs have large chicks to feed;
有些刚刚开始繁殖
others are just beginning to bred.
这些孤立岛屿上没有陆上猎兽
There are no land predators
on these islated islands,
所以鸬鹚不需飞行逃走
so there's nothing here that
the cormorants need fly away from
时间一久它们失去飞行能力
over time, they've lost the power of flight -
它们走路或者游泳
instead they walk or swim.
鸬鹚只有几百对
There are just a few hundred
pairs of cormorants.
它们只栖息在一年克伦威尔
海流流经的地方
They live only where the Cromwell
Current wells up, year round,
在加拉帕哥斯群岛西面
on the western Galapagos Islands.
所有准备好面对这些寒冷水域的
动物都大快朵颐
All the animals that are prepared
to brave these icy waters dine well.
海生鬣蜥在加拉帕哥斯群岛
比比皆是
Marine iguanas are found throughout
the Galapagos Island group
但西面的鬣蜥是最大最肥的
but these ones in the west are
by far the biggest and fattest.
日出时鬣蜥一如平时等待着
It's dawn, and the iguanas are
playing their usual waiting game.
这些爬行动物和它们忍受的
长夜一样寒冷
These reptiles are now as cold as
the long night they've just endured
它们要晒一会儿太阳后才觅食
they need to heat up in the
sun before they can feed.
寒冷令最大的雄蜥焦躁
Cold makes the largest males grumoy.
冰冷鬣蜥不只要等晒数小时太阳
才能让身体暖和得足以觅食
Cool iguanas not only have to wait for hours
until the sun warms them enough to feed
它们也要忍受附近忙碌的鸬鹚
they must also tolerate their
busy cormorant neighbours.
鸬鹚高近一米
让晒太阳的鬣蜥相形见拙
Nearly a metre hall,
the cormorants dwarf the basking iguanas.
温血鸟类无需等待就可以进冷水
The warm-blooded birds don't need
to wait to get in the cold water
这对热恋鸬鹚自日出就在跳舞
this courting pair have
been dancing since dawn.
在这里做不懂飞行的鸟类很好
This is a great place to
be a flightless bird
雄鸬鹚永远不需离开巢外几百米
a male cormorant never needs to travel
more than a few hundred metres from his nest.
寒冷的克伦威尔海流提供一切
The cold Cromwell Current
provides everything
包括它一定要带给同巢鸬鹚的
大量新鲜藻类
including the gifts offresh algae
he must bring to his nest mate.
雌鸬鹚将藻类砌成鸟巢
The female adds the gift to the
collection she's fashioning into a nest
完成后巢就会高得足以
防止卵撞上硬石
when complete, it'll be just high enough
to keep her eggs off the hard rock.
将近中午时邻近的鸬鹚
已经忙了几小时
By mid-morning, when the nearby cormorants
have already been busy for hours,
饥饿的鬣蜥只是刚刚开始活动
the hungry iguanas are only just
beginning to show signs of action.
第一批雄性大鬣蜥慢慢爬到水边
The first big males slowly make
their way down to the water's edge.
食草鬣蜥有很不寻常的生活方式
The vegetarian iguanas have
a most unlikely lifestyle,
只有在赤道才可能
one that's only possible here,
at the Equator
热带太阳的热力让它们能够
忍受寒冷海水
where the heat of there tropical sun
allows them to endure the chilly waters.
离岸几百米处是冷海流栽培的
繁茂藻类花园
Just a few hudred metres offshore, nurtured by
the cold current, there are lush algae gardens.
但只有雄性大鬣蜥有足够的
块头抵受泠水
But only the largest males have enough
body mass to survive the chill waters
小鬣蜥则会失温过快而死
a small iguana would lose
heat too quickly and die.
只有雄性大鬣蜥潜入水里
寻找藻类最丰富的地方
Only big males dive down to feed
where the algae is most lush.
但为什么这雄性大鬣蜥能够
忍受摄氏16度水温
But how can even this large male survive
water that's just 16 degrees Celsius,
这温度低得足以杀死
冷血爬行动物
low enough to kill a
cold-blooded reptile?
一只潜水的雄鬣蜥将血
抽离身体表面
A diving male moves blood
away from his body surface,
转而保存主要器官的热力
to help conserve heat in his core organs.
它也大幅减少心跳率
He also drastically lowers his heart rate
这样它就能抵受体温下降15度
By doing this, he can survive a
fifteen degree drop in body temperature.
上午将尽
As the morning wears on,
其他大鬣蜥身体
够暖和了，纷纷潜水
other big iguanas become warm
enough to take the plunge.
一只雄鬣蜥的长爪钩着
凹陷的火山熔岩
A male hooks his long claws
into the pitted volcanic lava,
准备面对海浪上升
as he braces himself against
the wave surge.
鬣蜥食量惊人
Iguanas are voracious eaters.
它们会将藻类吃个干净
They clip the algae until it
看来像是新草地
looks like a newly mown lawn.
但藻类在这丰饶水域生长迅速
But algae grows fast in these rich waters
几天后又能喂给鬣蜥
and can be grazed again in just a few days,
潜水的鬣蜥一定要尽快吃藻类
A diving iguanas must feed quickly,
它是陆地动物
经常要浮上水面呼吸
Being a land animal,
he surfaces often to breath.
它最多只能在冷水里两小时
And he can only survive the cold
water for two hours at the most,
之后就一定要回到岸上
before he must head back to shore.
雄性大鬣蜥潜了好一阵子的水后
非常寒冷
After a long dive,big males
are so chilled,
几乎无法游动
they 're barely able to swim.
如果它们冲出海洋就会必死无疑
If they're swept out to sea,
they'll face certain death.
每只都要奋力游回温暖岸边
Each must fight his way back
to the warm shore.
潮水最终低得露出最浅的藻床
At last the tide is low enough to
expose the shallowest algae beds.
较小的雌鬣蜥和年轻鬣蜥
终于可以进食
finally, the smaller females
and young iguanas can feed.
但它们也要尽快
But they, too, must hurry
它们要和转变的潮水斗快
they're in a race against the turning tide.
海生鬣蜥和另一种热带爬行动物
分享藻类花园
Marine iguanas share the rich algae gardens
with another tropical reptile.
和鬣蜥一样
加拉帕哥斯群岛绿龟
Like the iguanas,
the Galapagos green turtle
在冷水里行动缓慢
is slow and sluggish in the cold.
绿龟没有鬣蜥的爪抵挡浪涛
It lacks an iguana's claws
to hold on in the swell,
但它们锲而不舍
but it's persistent
生长迅速的藻类值得它们这样做
and the fast-growing algae
is well worth the effort.
对西岛的动物来说
For the inhabitants of
the western islands,
克伦威尔海流是可靠提供者
the Cromwell Current is
a reliable provider.
但在较难预测的东岛又怎样？
But what's happening in the less
predictable world of the eastern islands?
现在是五月初
太阳让水面升温至25度
Right now, in early May, the sun has heated
the surface water to 25 degrees
海水清澈，提供的食物不多
it's clear, and offers little food.
加拉帕哥斯群岛企鹅同时住在
寒冷西岛和温暖东岛
Galapagos penguins live in both the
cold western and warm eastern islands.
在东方，时间很难熬
In the east, times are hard
但这里的企鹅期望着
食物丰富的冷水很快到达
but penguins here are gambling on a rich,
cold water bonanza arriving soon.
蝴蝶鱼找到喜爱的温暖海水
Butterfly fish fine the warm
waters very much to their liking.
但和帕米拉环礁不同
这里没有太多珊瑚
However, unlike Palmyra there's
not much coral here to feed on,
所以它们改变了生活方式
so they've changed lifestyles.
一些蝴蝶鱼现在吃寄生虫
Some butterfly fish now eat parasites
它们成了清洁鱼
they have become cleaner fish.
要在这里生存
To survive here
你要适应
不然就要死
you adapt or die.
对海岸鸟类而言
For some coastal birds,
岛屿附近的温暖海水和海洋一样
是毫无生命的沙漠
the warm water around the islands is as
much a lifeless desert as the open ocean.
但这些蓝脚鲣鸟和企鹅一样
However, like the penguins,
these blue footed boobies
期望着冷水到来
are gambling on the arrival of cold water,
幼鸟能够有充足食物
rich in food for hungry chicks.
这一对蓝脚鲣鸟刚刚交往
This pair is in the early stages of courtship.
接下来几天它们的关系
会更进一步做一些例行动作
Over the next few days they'll deepen
their relationship with ritual displays
和开始选择筑巢地
and begin the task of choosing a nest site.
这一对蓝脚鲣鸟刚刚开始
This pair is just starting
但其他蓝脚鲣鸟已经生下幼鸟
but others already have chicks.
成双成对的蓝脚鲣鸟群落处于
不同繁殖阶段
Throughout the colony pairs are
at different stages of breeding
但未来无法肯定
让后代冒上生命危险
but all are gambling the lives of
their offspring on an uncertain future.
这一对蓝脚鲣鸟很早筑巢
This pair nested early
如果冷水很快到达
它们就会是赢家
They'll be winners if the
cold water arrives soon.
它们有两只蛋，其他的鸟有三只
They have two eggs, others have three.
它们也许能养大所有幼鸟
或者一只也养不大
They might raise all their
chiks or none it all
全要看食物何时到达
depends on when the food arrives.
一只雄性蓝脚鲣鸟在离巢不远处
潜进水里觅食
A male blue footed booby dives
for food, not far from the nest.
但水仍然是暖的
But the water is still warm
它只是徒劳无功
there's little reward for all his hard work.
它和伴侣是最早繁殖的
He and his mate were among
the earliest to breed.
最初有三只蛋
They started with three eggs
但它们只找到
足够一只幼鸟吃的食物
but they're only finding enough
food for a single chick
目前它们没有转运的迹象
and at the moment there's no sign
of a change in their fortunes.
这幼鸟生存与否要看地球的轨道
This chick's survival depends
on the Earth's Orbit
和太阳的位置
and the position of the sun.
太阳向北半球移动
As it moves towards the northern hemisphere,
带着贸易风和海洋水流
it's bringing trade winds
and ocean currents with it
对鲣鸟来说，这意味着富足
and for the boobies,
the promise of plenty.
鲣鸟不只冒季节转变
何时开始的险
The boobies are notjust gambling on
when the change in season will happen.
也面对着即时的问题
They have a more immediate problem.
这年轻军舰鸟已经学会
偷勤劳的鲣鸟的食物
This young frigate bird is already learning
to steal food from the hard-working boobies.
军舰鸟的成功相当依靠
鲣鸟的运气
Frigate bird success relies heavily
on the fortunes of the boobies,
所以它们将繁殖选在这个时候
so they've timed their breeding
to coincide with them.
军舰鸟现在繁殖
冷水来临时也会受惠
By breeding now frigate birds will also
benefit when the cold water arrives.
如果鲣鸟没事
这些小偷也会繁衍
If boobies do well,
then there pirates will thrive
如果水继续暖和
它们就会受苦
if the water stays warm,
they'll both suffer.
雌军舰鸟在空中飞过
As female fly overhead,
一群雄军舰鸟争相以红色气囊
取悦它们
a group of males compete to impress
them with the redness of their air sacs,
它们使劲叫嚷抖动
and the vigorousness of their
calling and shaking.
这地方难以居住
This is a rough beighbourhood.
一只收集树枝筑巢的红脚鲣鸟
A red footed booby collecting
sticks to build a nest
一定要面对空中盗贼
must run a gauntlet of aerial pirates
它们既偷树枝又偷食物
as intent on thieving sticks
as they are food.
军舰鸟翅膀张开超过两米
身体轻巧
With a wingspan of more than two metres,
and an amazingly light body,
是飞行技术高超的恶棍
a frigate bird is an aerobatic thug
能够在空中偷掉鲣鸟嘴里的树枝
able to steal sticks out
a booby's beak in mid air.
鲣鸟掉下树枝
The booby drops its stick
但敏捷的军舰鸟轻松地捡起来
but the agile trigate bird just swoops it up.
偷窃是非常危险的做法
Thievery is a very risky strategy
这对军舰鸟只会养一只幼鸟
so much so that this pair will raise just a single chick.
这是艰巨的工作
It's an epicjob
它们的后代要一年半
才能学会空中偷窃
it will be a year and a half before their
offspring masters the dark art of aerial piracy.
尚在学习的小偷连成年军舰鸟
也会下手
Even an adult frigate bird is a fair target,
for an apprentice pirate.
资源竞争非常激烈
Competition for resources is so intense,
军舰鸟要一直保持警觉
在巢里也不例外
that frigate birds always have
to be on guard even at the nest.
军舰鸟和鲣鸟认为
冷水会带来食物
Frigate birds and boobies are gambling
that cold water will bring them food
信天翁相信会带来凉爽天气
the albatrosses trust it
will bring cool weather
希望很快来临
hopefully soon.
尽管信天翁是寒冷气候的鸟类
Although albatrosses are cold climate birds,
加拉帕哥斯群岛是
弄潮信天翁的栖息地
the Galapagos Islands are home
to wave albatrosses,
唯一的热带信天翁
the only truly tropical species.
它们只在这里繁殖
This is the only place they breed,
它们来这里，因为这里是
没有猎兽的安全地方
and they're here because it's a safe,
predator-free haven.
但对回来的雌信天翁并不安全
But it's not so safe for a returning female.
它一定要穿过一群雄信天翁
She must run a gauntlet of males,
它们都想和它交配
hell-bent on mating with her.
这些信天翁都不是
雌信天翁的伴侣
Neither of these males is this female's mate
1/4幼鸟不是养育它们的
雄信天翁的后代
Around a quater of all chicks are not
fathered by the male who raises them.
对信天翁而言
Among albatrosses,
强奸和住在赤道同样意料不到
rape is as unexpected as living at the Equator
但这些是加拉帕哥斯群岛
but these are the Galapagos Islands,
奇怪和不可能的事会发生
where strange and improbable things happen.
信天翁和军舰鸟一样
只养一只幼鸟
Like frigate birds, albatrosses
raise just one chick
这工作需要一对信天翁
近八个月时间
The task will take a pair
nearly eight months.
它们交配前几星期前互相展示
For weeks before they begin,
they display to each other.
这是保证尽管和其他信天翁交配
it's a way of ensuring that,
despite all the extra matings,
两只鸟仍会一起做这漫长的工作
both birds will be committed
to the lengthy task ahead.
这一对信天翁长时间的仪式
加强它们的联系
The pair's prolonged ritual
strengthens their bond,
为了它们分离过活的长时期
for the long periods they spend apart.
它们在1500公里外觅食
They feed fifteen hundred kilometres away,
在秘鲁海岸外上升的冷水
in cold water upwellings off the
coast of Peru.
每只鸟或许要离开两星期
Each bird may be away for two weeks at a time,
但这次长旅程是值得的
but the long journey is well worth it.
信天翁的觅食地非常富饶
The albatrosses' feeding grounds
are incredibly rich
这些觅食地是加拉帕哥斯群岛的
动物等待的关键
and they're the key to what the animale
of the Galapagos are waiting for.
太阳不仅制造太平洋的海洋水流
The sun not only generates Pacific's ocean currents,
也能移动水流
it has the power to move them around.
五月时，太阳向北移动
During May, when the sun is moving north,
东南贸易风正在加强
the south-east trade winds are gatheribg strength.
到时候就会将秘鲁海岸的
洪堡洋流拖向北面
When they're strong enough, they'll drag the cold
Humboldt Current northwards from the coast of Peru.
一层云会预示冷水到来
The arrival of the cold water
is marked by a layer of cloud
这是丰饶的清凉季节
称为浓湿雾
this is the cool season of plenty
known as the 'garua'.
但这时
But at the moment,
东岛仍被温暖贫瘠的水包围
the eastern islands remain surrouded
by warm barren water.
只得西岛有食物
Only the western islands have food.
多得可靠的洪堡洋流
thanks to the reliable Crownwell Current,
雄性大鬣蜥在藻类花园
进食了两小时
The big male iguana's been feeding
in the algae gardens for two hours.
它现在很冷
He's now so cold,
连吃进去的藻类也消化不了
He not even capable of digesting the algae he's just eaten.
应该提高体温了
It's time to warm up again.
寒冷的鬣蜥把自己靠在热石上
Cold iguanas press themselves against
the hot rock for maximum warming.
雄性大鬣蜥吸引热力时
身体慢慢恢复活动
As the big male absorbs heat,
activity slowly returns to his body.
只有等它的体温恢复至35度
才能消化胃里的藻
Only when his temperature reaches 35 degrees
can he digest the algae in his stomach.
一只年轻鸬鹚打扰晒太阳的鬣蜥
A young cormorant bothers the sunbathing iguanas,
只因为它有恃无恐
just because it can.
尽管有恼人的邻居
Despite the annoying neighbours,
加拉帕哥斯群岛有一切支持
鬣蜥异常生活方式的情况
the Galapagos Islands have all the conditions
to support the iguanas unusual lifestyle,
像焗炉一样散发热力的黑熔岩
The black lava, which radiates heat like an oven
和中午的烈日
and the intense midday sun a blessing
让两个截然不同的世界同时并存
that makes life between two
very different worlds possible.
雄鸬鹚整天在冷水进出收集藻类
The male cormorant is in and out of the
cold water all day collecting algae gifts.
它没有注意到岸上变得多热
He doesn't notice how hot it's become ashore.
但对一些动物来说
无情的中午热力是诅咒
But for some animals,
the merciless midday heat is a curse.
所有筑巢鸟类都面对太阳的考验
All nesting birds are facing trial by sun.
鸬鹚群的地面温度接近40度
Ground temperatures in the cormorant
colony have climbed into the thirties
但成年鸬鹚无法躲避
but the adults can't escape.
它们要看守蛋和幼鸟
They're trapped by their eggs and chicks.
赤道太阳划过天空
As the equatorial sun moves across the sky,
一只鲣鸟转身躲避酷热
a booby turns to face away from its burning heat
在巢边制造鸟粪日晷
creating a guano sundial around its nest.
它扬起背部羽毛
想要挡着凉风
It raises the feathers on its back,
trying to catch a cool breeze.
一只幼鸟在父母的身影下
A chick shelters in shade cast by its parent.
但成年鸬鹚无处遮阴
but there's no shade for the adults.
孵化的信天翁喘气驱热
An incubating albatross pants to lose heat.
它的父母直觉会受到最大考验
its parental instincts tested to the limit
直至凉快的浓湿雾到来
until the cool garua arrives.
海狮较轻松
Sealions have it easier
一天最热的时候可以滑水
during the hottest part of the day they go surfing.
加拉帕哥斯群岛的气候反复无常
On the Galapagos Islands climate is unpredictable
情况每天每年改变
conditions change from day to day, year to year.
生物尽量应对不稳定情况
Creatures deal with the uncertainty as best they can.
鲣鸟幼鸟，孵化了
A booby chick hatches
但它的未来会怎样？
but what will its future hold?
今天它有食物
There's food for it today
但明天能吃饱吗？
but will it get fed tomorrow?
冷水何时来到？
When will the cold water arrive?
如果不来的话会怎样？
And what happens if it doesn't arrive at all?
每隔几年岛就会
被温暖贫瘠的水包围
Every few years the islands remain
surrounded by warm empty water
这叫做厄尔尼诺
This is called El Nino
所有依靠冷水来临的动物
都要受苦
All the animals that depend on the
coming of the cold water, suffer.
厄尔尼诺严重的话
In a severe El Nino,
连可靠的克伦威尔海流都来不到
even the reliable Cromwell Current may fall
后果不堪设想
the effect is devastating.
海狮和小海豹饿死
Sea lions and seal pups starve to death.
只有腐肉食动物过着好日子
Only scavengers do well.
很多鲣鸟离巢而去
Many booby desert their nests,
留下熔岩海鸥吃遗下的蛋
leaving lava gulls to feast on abandoned eggs.
死亡逼近鲣鸟群
Death stalks the booby colony.
只有最强壮的幼鸟能够生存
Only the strongest chicks survive.
最近一次厄尔尼诺引致
很多鬣蜥死亡
In a recent El Nino, many iguanas died
但其他鬣蜥靠缩小生存下来
but others cheated death by shrinking.
它们的身体，包括骨头
缩小了近1/4
Their whole body, including skeleton,
shrank by nearly aquarter.
缩小的幸存者可以靠较少
和较差的食物生存
shrunken survivors could exist on less,
poor quality food.
鬣蜥一定要灵活变通
Iguanas must always be resourceful
它们这样才能在这些
沙漠岛上生存
it's how they survive on these
desert islands.
它们每天都要抵受酷热
Each day they walk a thermal tightrope
近傍晚的时候，连鬣蜥都太热了
by mid afternoon, even the iguqnas are too hot.
它们不碰发烫的地面让自己凉快
They push their bodies off the hot ground to cool themselves
彷彿它们想要看看
来临的浓湿雾
it's as if they're trying to catch a glimpse of the coming garua.
远处的云预示浓湿雾快将来临
Clouds on the horizon hint it might be near
但也许这近在眼前，却无影无迹
but it's come this close before, and still failed.
日落时分
生物暂且获得片刻抒缓
Sunset grants the animales of the
Galapagos a temporary reprieve.
鬣蜥现在冒着体温过低的风险
The iguanas now risk becoming too cool.
但对海鸟来说
but for the seabirds
长夜让它们松一口气
the long night will be a blessed relief.
对海狮来说，黑暗带来新可能
For the sea lions, darkness brings new possibilities.
它们现在可以在水下悬崖
猎食睡着的鱼
They can now hunt for sleeping fish on underwater cliffs.
热天已经很长时间了
As long hot days turn into weeks,
云慢慢在岛上积聚
clouds slowly gather over the islands,
冷水快到这里了
The cold water is almost here.
这是今年小鬣蜥的好时机
It's good timing for this year's iguana hatchlings.
这小鬣蜥花了几天
This baby iguana has spent days,
挖开孵化的地方
在沙滩碎石深处
digging its way up from where it hatched,
deep in the beach gravel.
它首次出现在地面上
Above ground for the first time,
尝试免让其他动物发现
一边盘算最好的逃跑地方
it tries to avoid detection while
it works out the best place to run.
这小鬣蜥一定要走过
空旷沙滩的无人之地
The hatchling must cross a
no-man's land of empty beach.
到达可以安全藏身的石头
to reach rocks where it can safely hide.
它做到了
It makes it.
小鬣蜥直觉知道
会在海里找到好运
Instinctively the young iguana knows that
it'll find its fortune from the sea
尽管它要过几年身体长大后
才能潜进水里
although it'll be many years before
it's big enough to dive down
在克伦威尔海流富饶的
藻类花园觅食
to feed in the rich algae
gardens of the Cromwell Current.
季节终于改变
Finally, the seasons change
冷水到达了
the cold water arrives,
每次总是伴随着厚云
accompanied by its trademark heavy cloud.
这是浓湿雾季节
This is the season of the garua.
浓雾形成，赤道太阳和洪堡洋流
冷水互动
The dense mist forms as the hot equatorial sun
interacts with the cold water of the Humboldt Current.
浓湿雾带来较凉快的温度
The garua brings cooler temperatures
弄潮信天翁现在舒服一点
waved albatrosses are more comfortable now.
一只虚弱的鲣鸟运气好
A weak booby chick is in luck
今年它会有食物
there will be food for it
this year, after all.
在这巢里两只幼鸟都会生存
In this nest, both chicks will survive.
不只鲣鸟可以繁衍
It's not just the boobies who prosper
军舰鸟也会
so will the frigate birds.
对所有海洋生物来说
For all the creatures of the sea,
浓湿雾到来是难以置信的
丰饶时候的开始
the coming of the garua is the beginning
of an incredible time of plenty.
西部的克伦威尔海流
是可靠的全年提供者
In the west, the Cromwell Current
is a reliable year-round provider.
在东部，每年有几个月
In the east, for a few months each year,
强大的洪堡洋流
带来难以想像的财富
the powerful Humboldt Current
brings unimaginable wealth
丰富的冷水，由南极一直到赤道
rich cold water, all the way
from Antarctica to the Equator,
来到加拉帕哥斯群岛
here at the Galapagos Islands.
赤道太阳的威力
和冷水水流的矿物
The power of the equatorial sun
and the minerals in the cold current
是激发生命暴增的火花
are the sparks that ignite an explosion of life
浮游生物生长非常迅速
遮蔽了阳光
plankton grows so quickly and thickly,
it dims the light.
浮游生物分布非常广阔
The plankton blooms are so vast,
在太空也看得到
they can be seen from space
给贸易风吹到西面
blown to the west by the trade winds.
大量的萨利马鱼群是东岛企鹅
等待已久的宝物
Enormous schools of salimas are the bonanza the
penguins of the eastern islands have been waiting for.
这一年所有依靠海洋的动物
都有好日子过
This is a good year for all animales
that depend on the sea.
海洋水流，因为赤道太阳而动
Ocean currents, set in motion by the equatorial sun,
带来肯定和财富
have brought certainty and wealth.
生命在这些疑幻疑真的
沙漠岛繁衍
Life prospers on these improbable
desert islands
在冷水的绿州上
in an oasis of cold water,
由太阳…
created by the power of the sun.
和海洋的能量催生
and the power of the ocean.